Finding Aid for Arthur Whitmore Smith Papers, 1893-1954
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Arthur Whitmore Smith papers 1893-1954 1930-1954
Smith, Arthur Whitmore, 1874-1954.
1 linear feet
861 Aa 2
Professor of Physics at the University of Michigan. Correspondence and other papers relating to his research in physics, and his interest in his family genealogy and his activities with the Sons of the American Revolution in Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Arthur Smith (Donor No. 4896 ) in April 1970.
The collection is open to research.
Dr. Arthur Whitmore Smith was born in Hartford, Vermont on May 11, 1874. After receiving his B.S. degree in 1893 from the University of New Hampshire, he continued his education at Wesleyan University, receiving a Masters of Science in 1895. Dr. Smith completed his Ph.D. in physics at Johns Hopkins University in 1903.
Throughout his career, Dr. Smith held numerous teaching assignments including positions at Wesleyan University and the University of Mississippi. In 1903, he came to the University of Michigan where he taught in the physics department until his retirement in 1944. During his forty-one years at the University of Michigan, Dr. Smith wrote numerous articles. His special area of study concerned the calorimetric determination of the energy of food.
Dr. Smith's hobby was genealogy which he pursued throughout his life. He was involved with many organizations dealing with genealogical research. For example, he served as both vice-president and president of the Michigan Society of the Sons of the American Revolution. Furthermore, Dr. Smith helped found an Ann Arbor chapter of the Institute of American Genealogy.
Dr. Smith remained active as a professor until his death on December 1, 1954.
The papers of Dr. Arthur Whitmore Smith consist of correspondence and other papers relating to his research in physics, and his interest in his family genealogy and his activities with the Sons of the American Revolution in Michigan. The papers are arranged in four series: Biographical Information, Genealogical Activities, Physics Research, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Genealogy.; Physics.; Smith family.; Smith, Arthur Whitmore, 1874-; Sons of the American Revolution. Michigan Society.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Smith, Arthur Whitmore, 1874-; University of Michigan--Buildings.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical Information
  The Biographical Information series (1 folder) provides useful information about Smith's life and includes his curriculum vitae, a bibliography of his scholarly writings, citations, clippings, and biographical information used Who's Who and similar volumes. The folder contains documents dated from around 1895 to the 1940s.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Genealogical Activities
  The Genealogical Activities series (4 folders) concerns Dr. Smith's research of his family's genealogy. This series includes two folders of correspondence dating from 1930 to 1954 detailing his own genealogical pursuits as well as his activities with the Michigan Society of the Sons of the American Revolution and the formation of the Ann Arbor chapter of The Institute of American Genealogy. Also, this series contains a notebook with Smith's genealogical research on his own family.
  - Ann Arbor Genealogical and Historical Society, undated 1940s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1954, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan Society of the Sons of the American Revolution, 1934-1950 (Box 1)
  - Smith family (and related) genealogical research, 1 volume and 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw Impressions article, "Looking for Ancestors" 1946 (Box 1)
- Physics Research
  The Physics Research (3 volumes and 2 folders) series contains the published and unpublished writings of Dr. Smith. Two of these volume are reprints of journal articles covering the years 1893 to 1948. Also included is a textbook entitled Electrical Measurements in Theory and Application. There is also a folder of unpublished writings about magnetism. In addition, there is a diary of personal observations and newspaper clippings kept by Smith about an experiment he conducted in 1896 to test the energy produced by different foods using a calorimeter.
  - Diary of Calorimeter experiment, 1896 (Box 1)
  - Calorimetric Research of Arthur W. Smith, 1894-1900 (Box 1)
    (consists of bound set of scientific reprints)
  - Researches in Physics, 1893-1948 (Box 1)
  - Electrical Measurement in Theory and Application, 1948, 1 volume and 1 folder (Box 1)
    (includes corrections to the book)
  - Manuscripts of writings on magnetism, undated (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The Photograph series (1 folder) consists of both individual and family pictures as well as photographs of the University of Michigan campus and buildings.
  - Portraits, 1920s-1930s campus views, ca. 1946 showing Chemistry Building and view of Rackham Building taken from South University; and snapshot of Monroe Street residence, 1949 (Box 1)